Guide to the Julia R. Grout Papers, 1916 - 1984
University Archives Duke University
Julia R. Grout papers 1916 - 1984
Grout, Julia R.
0.75 Linear Feet, 500 Items
University Archives, Duke University
Julia Rebecca Grout (1898-1984) served as Chairman of the Women's Department of Health and Physical Education at Duke University from 1924 to 1964. The Julia R. Grout Papers include correspondence, clippings, writings, printed matter, photographs, and other materials related to Grout's professional and personal interests. Topics include Grout's career and retirement; the history of physical education at Duke; comparisons of American and European physical education; physical education for women; Grout's travels to Southern Africa and Europe; and Grout's participation in the Dedication Committee of Baldwin Auditorium at Duke.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The Julia R. Grout Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift from 1972-1986.
Biographical Note
Julia Rebecca Grout, known to most as Jerry, was born on April 1, 1898 in North Brookfield, Massachusetts. She attended Mount Holyoke College, where she was an outstanding athlete, and received her bachelor's degree in 1920. She received a Master of Science from Wellesley College in 1928.
Almost all of Grout's career was spent at Duke University. She arrived in 1924 and soon became Director (later called Chairman) of Physical Education for Women, a position she held until her retirement in 1964. During her tenure, the department offered a wide variety of required and elective physical education courses, oversaw recreational and athletic activities, and encouraged women students to be physically active. Grout was an advocate for improved facilities for women students, which is documented in her departmental memoir, As You Were, or Forty Years of Happenings in the Department of Health and Physical Education, The Woman's College, Duke University, 1924-1964. This memoir can be found in the Addresses and Writing series of these papers.
After her retirement in 1964, Grout remained an active, travelling frequently and staying in close contact with her colleagues at Duke University. She died on April 22, 1984.
Collection Overview
The Julia R. Grout Papers include correspondence, clippings, writings, printed matter, photographs, and other materials related to Grout's professional and personal interests. The papers are divided into four series. The Personal series includes Grout's resume, retirement materials, tributes to her, and documents related to her funeral. One of the retirement materials is a large bound volume of letters written to Grout by students and colleagues expressing their appreciation for her forty years of service at Duke. The second series, Correspondence, has a brief selection of letters related to Grout's professional career, her 1958 travels to Southern Africa, and work on the Dedication Committee of Baldwin Auditorium. The third series, Addresses and Writings, includes a variety of speeches, papers, and reports written by Grout over her career. Topics include the need for physical education for women, American physical education compared to that of Europe, and the history of physical education for women at Duke. Also included in this series are several speeches made by Grout at the retirement parties of other faculty and staff of the Woman's College. The final series, Professional Travels, documents Grout's international travels to Europe in 1938 and 1958, where she studied the physical education programs of Sweden, Holland, and Norway.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Duke University. Baldwin Auditorium
Duke University -- Faculty
Duke University. Women's Dept. of Physical Education
Grout, Julia R.
Photographs
Physical education and training -- Europe
Physical education and training -- Study and teaching (Higher)--United States
Physical education for women -- North Carolina -- History
Women travelers -- Africa -- Correspondence
Contents of Collection
- Personal, 1916-1984
  - Resume and CV (Folder 1)
  - Clippings, circa 1916-1960 (Folder 2)
  - Retirement, Bound Tribute Album, 1964 (Folder 3)
  - Retirement, Correspondence and Clippings, 1964-1965 (Folder 4)
  - Tributes, 1982-1984, undated (Folder 5)
  - Funeral Materials, 1984 (Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1953-1981
  - Professional, 1953-1981 (Folder 7)
  - African Trip, January 1958-February 1958 (Folder 8)
  - Dedication Committee of the Baldwin Auditorium, 1964 (Folder 9)
- Addresses and Writings, 1933-1979
  - Physical Education for Duke Women, August 1933 (Folder 10)
  - Keeping Physically Fit, circa 1940 (Folder 11)
  - Untitled, 1942, 1953 (Folder 12)
  - Assembly Talk, October 16, 1944 or October 16, 1946 (Folder 13)
  - Education Through Physical Education, Spring 1946 (Folder 14)
  - Skirts - Bloomers - Shorts: Highlights in the History of Women's Physical Education, December 11, 1946 (Folder 15)
  - Retirement party speeches, 1947-1979 (Folder 16)
  - History and Philosophy of the Department of Physical Education, Spring 1953 (Folder 17)
  - Physical Education Here and Abroad, circa 1958 (Folder 18)
  - A Study of Physical Education and Recreation Programs in Holland, Sweden, and Norway, 1958 (Folder 19)
  - Africa Notes, 1959-1963 (Folder 20)
  - In Support of Semester Hour Credit for Physical Education, December 14, 1961 (Folder 21)
  - Thirty-Three Years with the Altrusa Club, circa 1967 (Folder 22)
  - As You Were, or Forty Years of Happenings in the Department of Health and Physical Education, The Woman's College, Duke University, 1924-1964, circa 1970 (Folder 23)
  - Correspondence Regarding As You Were, 1970 (Folder 24)
  - Night Flying, [poem], undated (Folder 25)
- Professional Travels, 1938-1958
  - Swedish-American Course in Physical Education - Printed Materials, Reports, Photos, and Clippings, 1938 (Folder 26)
  - Sabbatical Study in Holland and Sweden - Reports and Photos, 1958 (Folder 27)
  - Sabbatical Study in Holland and Sweden - Research Materials, 1958 (Folder 28)
Related Material
Women's Department of Health and Physical Education Records
Duke University Archives
Woman's College Records
Duke University Archives
Grout Family Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Bibliography
Elizabeth C. Bookhout, Fifty Years of Physical Education for Duke Women, 1992